Inventory of the Herman Recht Papers 1943-1946
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Folders 501-600: 4 June 1945 to 5 September 1945
  - (6)
    - Folders 531- 540: 26 June 1945-1 July 1945 (6, 4)
      Talks about the income tax for men in the military. Actually describes his reaction to “Thrill of Romance”; hears that Marilyn Kaemmerle has been taken on as an editorial staff worker for the Freedom House, in New York City. Starts at his new job, which carries more responsibility, such as giving special liberties, and also has to teach the new person that is taking his old job. Goes out to dinner at the Capitol; goes and sees a lecture on Colonial Architecture in Latin America at PBK Hall; the Captain of the Camp, Capt. Perry, visits the camp library and is disturbed to find the magazines “PM” and “The New Republic” on the shelves, and that he also does not like having “niggers” in the camp; talks about how he approves of most of the politics of the Southern liberals, but cannot agree with their support of segregation. Hears that a lot of men are being transferred to Yorktown, and that Peary is receiving “Negro replacements”; hears a talk at William and Mary by Dr. William Schurz, of the Department of State, on the future of Inter-American relations. He leaves the most controversial issues, like Argentina and Brazil, out of his discussion; compares the treatment of “Brazilian Negroes” and those in the United States; talks with Dr. Schurz about his inability to speak freely, being a member of the State Department. Receives the “new Negro men” into the department, and begins training them. Gets a large group of civilians starting boot camp in at Peary; reads a quote by Governor Ellis Arnall of Georgia who says that the people of the South do not agree in “social equality with the Negro.” Sees a picture of the ship the Queen Mary in Life; is interested in the OPA and FEPC proceedings in Congress; reflects on the “anti-Negro matters.”
      Subseries 5: Folders 541-550: 2 July 1945- 9 July 1945
    - Folders 541-550: 2 July 1945- 9 July 1945 (6, 5)
      Lt. Kennedy is thinking about having twice monthly office meetings for the men to voice their concerns, as morale has been low the past month. Gets an electric water fountain in the office; writes a letter drunk. Talks about the different qualities of lives the he and some of his friends have, officers, rated men, and nonrated men. Kennedy talks about why his dad was fired from a steel mill: for trying to act independently and not give favor to other steel millers. Sees a copy of the pamphlet “Guide to Officers or Command of Negro Personnel;” reads an article in PM about the Pittsburgh public schools initiating a policy of teaching interracial and intercultural understanding through adult groups. Relates a story of a recently inducted sailor who is trying to get home to see his supposedly sick wife, although things seem odd in his story. There is no longer the “espirit de corps” that categorized the war effort before, but instead it has been replaced with a mere dull routine.
      Subseries 6: Folders 551-560: 10 July 1945-14 July 1945
    - Folders 551-560: 10 July 1945-14 July 1945 (6)
      Sees that a lot of the area around the hut is much nicer looking, with flowers, but is not sure if the men or the German prisoners did. Reads a reporter who disagrees with the official remarks that Germany has 75% of its industrial might left; reads an article from Virginius Dabney’s Paper that talks about the “anti-Negro venom spreaders” such as Theodore Bilbo of Mississippi and James Eastland, also of Mississippi. Is reading Agnes Meyer’s “Journey Thru Chaos,” which he find enlightening. The camp librarian is replaced with a new man who has to report directly to the Captain of the Camp. The branch library near the “Negro Barracks” is closed down suddenly. Few sailors are being assigned to the Atlantic fleet, and the Coast Guard is taking over much of that responsibility. Sees a deal for new Foreign Service Officers with the State Department, but the age requirement is 21-30 years old. Lt. Kennedy, and other section chiefs, are getting disgusted with the amount of men being transferred between sections. Gets Kennedy to help him try to transfer a “young Negro here” who is better trained to work in a different department. Many people like being at Camp Peary as opposed to being shipped out to sea; also gives just a general account of what he sees as the current mindset of the Seebees at Peary.
      Subseries 7: Folders 561-570: 14 July 1945- 19 July 1945
    - Folders 561-570: 14 July 1945- 19 July 1945 (6, 7)
      Hears a story about soldiers who were being shipped out on a train having to wear their dark blue uniforms in the sun, and reflects on the occasional arbitrariness of military orders. Reads the book The Brick Foxhole; says that soldiers complain about the Williamsburg USO, but says that it is not any better throughout much of the South. As more men depart the Camp, Recht notices that there is no longer and band and the Captain there to bid farewell to the soldiers. There has been confusion over if Recht will be allowed out of service on time, since he does not have a birth certificate; theorizes about Russia attacking Japan in a two front attack. Pokes fun at Esther for keeping all of his letters; sees the movie “Thousand and One Nights.” Lt. Kennedy has not told Recht whether or not he will institute Recht’s recommendation of conferences with the men, to see what the really are feeling; hears a rumor of more civilians being hired at the Camp. Reads a story in the Post-Gazette about how a Congressman got a passport for a wife to go visit her husband overseas. Hears that the German prisoners now have the job of cleaning the “heads” and says they have never been so clean; hears that the Navy is bombarding Japanese factories near the coast; includes a poem by Paul Laurence Dunbar. Buys more war bonds; reads about a Greyhound bus that fell into a river when the bridge collapsed; talks about the value of their record collection.
      Subseries 8: Folders 571-580: 19 July 1945-24 July 1945
    - Folders 571-580: 19 July 1945-24 July 1945 (6, 8)
      The District librarian is coming to visit the Camp library; has to give leave to a sailor whose mother is very sick. Plans to go see “Bell for Adano” with Lew, but it has not gotten good reviews. Reads a story in the Richmond paper about a plan for releasing men using a points system, but only people who have had 4 years of duty and will be 41 or older. Finally sees “Bell for Adano,” and likes it more than the reviews; reflects on whether his letters are more like letters or like “speech-making…and blowing off steam.” Goes to the Lodge and sits out by the pool, watching a 6 month old baby, before rain forces him inside. Meets a man from Maine, where Recht and Esther have traveled, and so they talk about places they have both been; men are complaining of getting bitten by flies; has a sailor tell him a story about how the sailor’s uncle sent him a letter saying that the sailor’s wife has been entertaining all sorts of men at their house, however the sailor thinks the uncle is sending these rumors because he wants to go on a date with his wife. Has an interesting experience of racism in the barber shop, with one barber hiding in the back office instead of cutting hair. Sees the movie “The Princess and the Bell Hop”; the coffee shop at the Lodge is now using saccharine tablets instead of sugar; hears from Frankie, and former sailor in their group, and that he is on an LST. Sees a “colored fellow” leading a group of men, both black and white, from induction to the mess hall; theorizes that the Nazi’s learned from the KKK and “other American methods of mistreatment of the Negro.”
      Subseries 9: Folders 581-590: 24 July 1945-28 July 1945
    - Folders 581-590: 24 July 1945-28 July 1945 (6, 9)
      Talks to a Y1c in the ship’s service office, who tells him that there will soon be two sets of barbers to try and prevent similar problems from happening. Reads Arthur Miller’s Situation Normal…; admits to some of the sailors that he had been a lawyer for 8 and a half years before joining the Navy. Reads about a white woman from Alexandria, Va, who was arrested for refusing to move from the back of the bus. Reflects on the defeat of Churchill’s party in the British Parliamentary elections; theorizes on what will happen to the Japanese, and how the Allies will attack them, mainly through more and more powerful air attacks, not a land invasion. Talks about the price and quality of clothes he can buy and try to send back home. Talks about playing checkers with a friend in the department; talks about the department picnic, with a “quartet of colored men singing.” Reads about peace terms, rather than surrender terms, that the Allies send the Japanese; talks with a man who has been working in the camp prison. Writes about an incident where white sailors followed “several young Negro girls” back to their house, where they were attacked by “Negroes” and also about another incident where a fight broke out about moving to the back of the bus; both of these incidents provoke a debate in Recht’s office; sees the movie “Junior Miss”; talks about one of the men in his office getting into a car crash at the intersection of Duke of Gloucester Street, Boundary Street, and Jamestown Road. Has some further comments about the fight on the bus; man who crashed the car gets two weeks restriction to base. Reads an article in Collier’s about the comparative income between races and why governments have failed to equalize it.
      Subseries 10: Folders 591-600: 29 July 1945-5 September 1945
    - Folders 591-600: 29 July 1945-5 September 1945 (6, 10)
      Talks about tree frogs that have congregated near his sleeping hut, because of all the rain. Writes in to PM Magazine, sending in some stories about his experience with it on the camp. Gets new men into his section, who are worse than the ones they are replacing; hears that the enlisted mens’ club is supposed to be finishing renovations soon. Hears a new order about how men found guilty of being away without leave are to be sent overseas, if physically fit. Lt. Kennedy shows Recht some pictures of him as an infant and a young child. Gets mold on his shoes from the amount of moisture in the air. Gets ready for a visit from Esther. Talks to the librarian’s wife, who is an ardent Mexican nationalist.
  Series 7: Folders 601-700: 5 September 1945 to 24 December 1945
- Folders 601-700: 5 September 1945 to 24 December 1945
  - (7)
      Subseries 1: Folders 601-610: 5 September 1945-12 September 1945
    - Folders 601-610: 5 September 1945-12 September 1945 (7, 1)
      His friend Lew talks about a book, By the Waters of Babylon, and how he thinks some parts of it are an unfair presentation of the Jews. Reads in the paper that the Navy will no longer allow sailors to wear civilian clothes when off-duty. Hears a rumor about the reduction of the amount of points needed to get a discharge; goes to a Billie Holliday concert where “many Negroes” were “specially invited;” hears that a lot of military surplus items are to become available to the public in a matter of weeks. Lt. Kennedy tells Recht that he is going to start looking for a man to replace him soon, as they both want to get out of the service; reads an article called “Race Relationships in the US.”
      Subseries 2: Folders 611-620: 12 September 1945-15 September 1945
    - Folders 611-620: 12 September 1945-15 September 1945 (7, 2)
      Uses pink paper one day, finding it to be the only thing on hand; the Navy finally recommends to sailors that they buy things at service prices and send them home, which is what sailors have been doing all along; remarks that the old camp soda fountain has been replaced by a sort of jewelry store. Hears a rumor about the replacement for Lt. Kennedy. Does not get anything out of the camp religious services. Finds out the public library is now closed in the evening to give the librarians a break; hears about how the personnel chief is disappointed about the test scores, on the General Classification Test, of the men staying in the Navy after the war ends. Lt. Kennedy finishes By the Waters of Babylon, and shares his views on it. A librarian puts up a sign that says “Jim Crow” with an “X” through it, and a “burly Southerner” causes a ruckus about it. Hears that the Secretary of the Navy is to appear before Congress to discuss demobilization; hears of many men and women having affairs with people all over the camp, including in Recht’s department; talks about living in the same house as Esther’s family.
      Subseries 3: Folders 621-630: 15 September 1945-19 September 1945
    - Folders 621-630: 15 September 1945-19 September 1945 (7, 3)
      Folders 621-630: 15 September 1945-19 September 1945
      Goes to the dentist. Researches getting insurance for a business. Has a Jewish service in the “Chapel of All Faiths,” which has a cross above the door. Esther gets some interesting ideas from the pink paper Herman sent her a letter upon; is about to get in 13 men to replace the 13 that are being shipped out from his department. Hears that Camp Peary is to become a general Navy boot camp; hears about yeomen being frozen. Hears about a group of men, who are not married and whose work is below average, being sent out to sea; goes to Richmond to a synagogue and hears a “hell-raising” sermon; sees the movie “The Southerner,” and thinks highly of it. Wonders about another trip by Esther down to Williamsburg. Reflects on having to live on less money than he is used to; has had some discussions with Young, his successor at his old job at the Camp, “about Negroes,” who says that they are not as smart as Whites. Finishes the novel The Folded Leaf.
      Subseries 4: Folders 631-640: 20 September 1945-23 September 1945
    - Folders 631-640: 20 September 1945-23 September 1945 (7, 4)
      Talks to a 3rd class Spec. X, who has been in the service 2.5 years, about what he did out of the service and what he has done while in the service; finds out that Esther is pregnant. Wants to get posters of “The Races of Mankind” from Fisk University for Brille, the librarian, to post in the library; talks about possible child names. Brille had been talking with Captain Perry’s wife and brought up Recht’s suggestion of distributing the Children’s Bureau pamphlets on Pre-Natal care, which she loved; wonders about using the Children’s Bureau aid for pregnant wives of servicemen; has Esther pick up a Suggested Reading list for him. Says that most of the men left only want one thing: to go home. After October 1, will no longer need to wear his white uniforms; researches the possibility of converting GI insurance into normal, private insurance. All people at the base are temporarily frozen in their current position, and instead of 1000 new recruits coming in, the number has risen to 2600. Rides to Richmond with Lew, in his newly repaired car. Is going to take a trip up to Pittsburgh to see Esther at the end of September; hears from Lew that Capt. Perry might want to take the top ten men at Peary, as measured by their service tests, and of which both Lew and Recht are members, and have them give lectures to men being discharged, about how to readjust; hears about a librarian who is a Russian Jew who has lived in Palestine most of his life, and paints, so Recht suggests to Brille that they show his work at the library. Sends home some towels that are “good enough for private use.” Hears more scuttle about the points system being changed, but nothing is firm yet; last winter, men packed dirt around the bottom of the Quonset hut Recht lives in to keep the wind from getting underneath.
      Subseries 5: Folders 641-650: 24 September 1945-28 September 1945
    - Folders 641-650: 24 September 1945-28 September 1945 (7, 5)
      Goes and visits a small Jewish deli in Newport News with Lew; visits the Navy Yard and explores Newport News some. Talks about coming back to Pittsburgh for October 3 through the 9th. Sees a film about Woodrow Wilson. Hears that the War Department wants 20 lawyers who speak German to go there for the War Guilt trials, but Recht does not wish to apply; fills up a box with towels, long underwear, jello, chocolate, and other things to send to Esther. Hears that they are going to reduce the amount of points needed to get out of the Navy to 40 on November 1, at which point Recht will have 40.5, however, the Navy has been slow at processing these men; might cancel next week’s leave for a longer 10 day leave later. Continues research on insurance companies. Is considering flying home instead of taking the bus. Recht’s department has been busy the past few days, partially because of the scheduling to bring in sailors from Williamsburg to watch the Camp play football against Little Creek; complains that the Navy does not recognize the fact that there are men of college training who would like some more intellectual magazines in the library. Hears about a clothing drive for war-ravages countries and suggests discharged men donate old uniforms. Gets information from the Children’s Bureau, sends some along to Esther and gives the rest to the library.
      Subseries 6: Folder 651-660: 28 September 1945- 17 October 1945
    - Folder 651-660: 28 September 1945- 17 October 1945 (7, 6)
      Reads “A Nation’s Gethsemane” by Powell Spring. Comments about the “explosive situation” of Zionism in Palestine. Sees that the PearyScope has been reduced in size, possibly to conserve paper. Many new sailors are arriving, all dressed in civilian clothes, and they give hope to the older sailors, who can go home as replacements come in; wishes to talk with an acquaintance from home who now publishes a Republican magazine. Sailors are at the College stadium for the game against Little Creek, but Recht does not want to take the chance of being out in the open without much clothes; hears that many ex-lawyers who joined the service do not want to go back to being lawyers. His watching being broken gets Recht up and into the office at 6:15 am. Wants Esther to tell him the reaction when people find out she is pregnant. Hears that the point requirement will remain 44 until January 1 194[6]. Criticizes the Navy for their policy of releasing men; hears a story about a famous football player, Trippi, released from the Army with 41 points, when 70 are required there.
      Subseries 7: Folder 661-670: 18 October 1945-24 October 1945
    - Folder 661-670: 18 October 1945-24 October 1945 (7)
      Theorizes that the reason that they cannot release as many people is because of all the sailors returning from the Pacific and being released first; hears that a show at the Ship’s Company theatre was delayed a half hour so that the CO and his group could finish ice cream sundaes. Feels that the Navy should pay him and other yeomen more money since they need them so much as to keep them longer than other sailors; talks about expanding a furniture for cash business he used to run. Talks about his interaction with Martin, a German PoW; talks about how the way to get towards true racial integration is to find the way to have people “want to treat Negroes like any other human being.” Gets a call in the middle of the night from a man who was supposed to leave at 0005 and the dispatcher read it as 0500. Talks with Kennedy about the way the demobilization is going. Thinks about compiling a list of music that would interest “infants and youngsters.” Has now been in the Navy for 2 years; wonders more about the “freezing” of yeomen; talks about his political affiliations in college. He and Lew talk with a man named Phillips, who is a Zionist and wants to have more information about Jews and other racial minorities in the Camp library; says that the Chaplins’ School at William and Mary is closing. Writes about how Bill Maudlin is now satirizing service officialdom; the Navy is reclaiming all mattresses issued to men when they arrived.
      Subseries 8: Folders 671-680: 25 October 1945-30 October 1945
    - Folders 671-680: 25 October 1945-30 October 1945 (7, 8)
      Takes the petty officer’s test without reading the manual, which talks about nautical terms. Calls in a reservation for Esther to come down November 21 to December 10; finds out that Virginia celebrates thanksgiving a week before the rest of the country; talks more about Esther’s pregnancy; hears that the current freeze on releasing yeomen will expire on January 1. Gets ribbed by some of his friends for writing letters that are too impersonal; talks about some of Esther’s friends encouraged her to leave him when he did not want to have children. Gets a “youngster” that is to begin training for his job, as his replacement. Wonders if he is becoming unusually critical of the Navy of late, with regards mainly to demobilization. Hears a man and his daughter talking about him and the fact that he works in an office, unlike the man’s daughter. Gets a telegram that a man’s newborn and wife are not doing well, and so Recht gets some one to find Lt. Kennedy as he is leaving church to sign the man’s leave form; continues to wonder about what he will do after the Navy. Talks the petty officer’s exam again, and says that it is for the last time, no matter what; talks about how a man got a “dependency discharge,” and how it annoyed the other men. Wants to get some records of lullabies for the baby; sees that Kennedy has put through a request to advance Recht to Y2c; talks about a broken relationship between “Sarah and dad,” which stemmed from the depression years. One of the librarians admits the Recht’s zeal for the library has gotten him excited about it. Gets a package marked express and perishable 11 days after it was sent.
      Subseries 9: Folders 681-690: 30 October 1945-22 November 1945
    - Folders 681-690: 30 October 1945-22 November 1945 (7, 9)
      Sees the movie “The Lost Weekend.” Talks with the recreation department sign painter, who had heard about him. Talks about how the morning is not a good time to write to Esther, as all the routine matters must be taken care of first. Changes Esther’s reservation to November 7 through November 24. Goes to see the singer Niles with Lew, and decides that if he does not like it, he can just go to the College library. Hears that the entire camp is scheduled to fold by June 1, although he should be out by then; finds out that his replacement-to-be does some sketching. Brille, the head librarian, returns from how, and Recht says that he will be happy to eat with him and Esther; is still intent on get Planned Parenthood information in the library. Hears that Brille has ordered the book Stork Bites Man, at Recht’s request. Notices that the boot training program has reached its planned peak of receiving 2000 new recruits a week; feels a little under the weather and tries a few different cures for it; takes over Shelor’s job for Thanksgiving while Boilieu, his replacement, takes over his job.
      Subseries 10: Folders 691-700: 25 November 1945-24 December 1945
    - Folders 691-700: 25 November 1945-24 December 1945 (7, 10)